<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<collection>
  <source/>
  <date>2019-08-05</date>
  <key/>
  <document>
    <id>26736037</id>
    <infon key="title">Single nucleotide polymorphism near CREB1, rs7591784, is associated with pretreatment methamphetamine use frequency and outcome of outpatient treatment for methamphetamine use disorder.</infon>
    <infon key="pmid">26736037</infon>
    <infon key="year">2016</infon>
    <infon key="month">1</infon>
    <infon key="day">7</infon>
    <infon key="journal">Journal of psychiatric research</infon>
    <infon key="journalISO">J Psychiatr Res</infon>
    <infon key="authors">Keith G Heinzerling, Levon Demirdjian, Yingnian Wu, Steven Shoptaw</infon>
    <infon key="chemicals">C115163|CREB1 protein, human	D000697|Central Nervous System Stimulants	D017362|Cyclic AMP Response Element-Binding Protein	D008694|Methamphetamine</infon>
    <infon key="meshHeadings">Qualifier|D000328|N|Adult	Qualifier|D019969|N|Amphetamine-Related Disorders%Descriptor|Q000235|Y|genetics	Qualifier|D002140|N|California	Qualifier|D000697|N|Central Nervous System Stimulants%Descriptor|Q000494|Y|pharmacology	Qualifier|D017362|N|Cyclic AMP Response Element-Binding Protein%Descriptor|Q000235|Y|genetics	Qualifier|D044465|N|European Continental Ancestry Group%Descriptor|Q000235|N|genetics	Qualifier|D005260|N|Female	Qualifier|D006630|N|Hispanic Americans%Descriptor|Q000235|N|genetics	Qualifier|D006801|N|Humans	Qualifier|D007198|N|Indians, North American%Descriptor|Q000235|N|genetics	Qualifier|D008297|N|Male	Qualifier|D008694|N|Methamphetamine%Descriptor|Q000494|Y|pharmacology	Qualifier|D020641|N|Polymorphism, Single Nucleotide	Qualifier|D012737|N|Sex Factors</infon>
    <passage>
      <offset>0</offset>
      <text>Single nucleotide polymorphism near CREB1, rs7591784, is associated with pretreatment methamphetamine use frequency and outcome of outpatient treatment for methamphetamine use disorder.</text>
      <infon key="section">title</infon>
    </passage>
    <passage>
      <offset>185</offset>
      <text>Although stimulant dependence is highly heritable, few studies have examined genetic influences on methamphetamine dependence. We performed a candidate gene study of 52 SNPs and pretreatment methamphetamine use frequency among 263 methamphetamine dependent Hispanic and Non-Hispanic White participants of several methamphetamine outpatient clinical trials in Los Angeles. One SNP, rs7591784 was significantly associated with pretreatment methamphetamine use frequency following Bonferroni correction (p &lt; 0.001) in males but not females. We then examined rs7591784 and methamphetamine urine drug screen results during 12 weeks of outpatient treatment among males with treatment outcome data available (N = 94) and found rs7591784 was significantly associated with methamphetamine use during treatment controlling for pretreatment methamphetamine use. rs7591784 is near CREB1 and in a linkage disequilibrium block with rs2952768, previously shown to influence CREB1 expression. The CREB signaling pathway is involved in gene expression changes related to chronic use of multiple drugs of abuse including methamphetamine and these results suggest that variability in CREB signaling may influence pretreatment frequency of methamphetamine use as well as outcomes of outpatient treatment. Medications targeting the CREB pathway, including phosphodiesterase inhibitors, warrant investigation as pharmacotherapies for methamphetamine use disorders.</text>
      <infon key="section">abstract</infon>
    </passage>
  </document>
</collection>
